<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BenH20 | Jan Heiland</title>
    <link>/tag/benh20/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/benh20/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>BenH20</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 15:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/logo_huc8d60562114d373ee9fcddf98bd2be5c_10437_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>BenH20</title>
      <link>/tag/benh20/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Riccati-Based Robust Controller Design for Index-1 Descriptor Systems and Standard Plants with Feedthrough</title>
      <link>/event/20-ecc-hinfric/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 15:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/20-ecc-hinfric/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Riccati-based approach to robust control is completely understood in theory
since long but seldom used for large-scale systems in practice. Only recently,
we have transferred iterative algorithms that allow the computation of solutions
to LQR Riccati equations in the large-scale setting to the indefinite Riccati
equations that appear in robust control. For descriptor systems, the relevant
Riccati equations are nonsymmetric and, for large-scale systems, there is no
established algorithm that can handle these even in the LQR case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we show how the general theory for descriptor systems with
index-1 pencil coincides with the theory for standard linear time invariant case
with feedthrough terms. This provides an algorithm to characterize and to
compute the solution to the generalized indefinite Riccati equations via
standard Riccati equations. In view of feasibility for large-scale descriptor
systems, we illustrate how to arrive at the equivalent standard Riccati-equation
without resorting to the canonical form used in the derivation of the
theoretical results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Riccati-based Robust Controller Design for Index-1 Descriptor Systems and Standard Plants with Feedthrough</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-20/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
