<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pendulum | Jan Heiland</title>
    <link>/tag/pendulum/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/pendulum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>pendulum</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 16:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/logo_huc8d60562114d373ee9fcddf98bd2be5c_10437_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>pendulum</title>
      <link>/tag/pendulum/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Control of a Triple Pendulum in Theory and Practice</title>
      <link>/event/20-pendulum-musen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 16:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/20-pendulum-musen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stabilization of a simple pendulum in the upright equilibrium is a common control task and can be realized with basic algorithms and basic hardware like Lego Mindstorm. The double pendulum is a popular example for a chaotic system which means that the influence of small perturbations leads to unpredictable behavior. Still, linear feedback controllers that counteract perturbations in real time are capable to stabilize equilibria of a double pendulum as well as trajectories. For the control of a triple pendulum, the same linear theory applies. The third segment, however, adds additional technical difficulties that need to be tackled with powerful hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, I will explain the principles of a linearization based 2-degrees of freedom controller design which is the combination of a feedforward control that prescribes a target trajectory and a feedback loop for stabilization of the system. For the nonlinear mathematical model of a triple pendulum, already the computation of the target trajectory and the feedforward control is a challenge. Further, I will discuss details of the implementation and practical problems that come with a physical setup.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Triple Pendulum</title>
      <link>/project/pendulum/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 11:56:57 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pendulum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our institute has a triple pendulum connected to a cart that can be controlled by a computer. Stabilizing a pendulum in upright position is a common control benchmark. Controlling a double or triple pendulum requires powerful hardware and a sophisticated and well-tuned software. The hardware was set up by the Magdeburg-based company Hasomed, the software has been developed in our institute for over 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The triple pendulum is used to test control algorithms in experiments. As opposed to pure simulations, the application in hardware comes with additional challenges like delays in communication and changing environmental parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the pendulum is used to showcase the need and potential of control algorithms in regular visits of students or the public at our annual long night of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;news&#34;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 11th: Visit of a project group from the Hubertus Gymnasium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 1st: In cooperation with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hasomed.de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hasomed&lt;/a&gt;, we revise the controller software and the interface to the hardware. The result will be test blocks for basic control tasks like the controlled transversion of the pendulum both in open loop and closed loop regimes. &lt;em&gt;HASOMED&lt;/em&gt; co-sponsors the development and will distribute the developed software under a license agreement with the MPI-MD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;pendulum-de.pdf&#34;&gt;poster&lt;/a&gt; explains the setup and the basic procedures of the control scheme as well as typical application areas (in German).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video shows the swingup and swingdown of the triple pendulum in slow motion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;









  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;/project/pendulum/triple_swingup_slomo.MP4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
