<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peter Benner | Jan Heiland</title>
    <link>/author/peter-benner/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/peter-benner/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Peter Benner</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 14:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/logo_huc8d60562114d373ee9fcddf98bd2be5c_10437_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>Peter Benner</title>
      <link>/author/peter-benner/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Methods in Control and Optimization of Dynamical Systems</title>
      <link>/event/23-bimos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/23-bimos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After an introduction into the basic notions and principles of dynamical systems and control, I will address the challenges that come with high-dimensional (or even infinite-dimensional) nonlinear systems and show some recent theoretical and numerical approaches to their solution. The findings and concepts are illustrated by applications to the Navier-Stokes model equations and to a real-world triple pendulum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If time suffices, I will address data-driven approaches that use data and possibly techniques from Machine Learning to enhance the models in terms of accuracy or faster evaluation times.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A low-rank solution method for Riccati equations with indefinite quadratic terms</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-hw-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-hw-23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A quadratic decoder approach to nonintrusive reduced-order modeling of nonlinear dynamical systems</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-ghp-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-ghp-23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Lag Synchronization of Cohen-Grossberg Neural Networks with Discrete and Distributed Delays on Time Scales</title>
      <link>/publication/kum-hb-23-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kum-hb-23-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frequency-dependent Switching Control for Disturbance Attenuation of Linear Systems</title>
      <link>/publication/zha-hbd-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/zha-hbd-23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MaRDIFlow: A Workflow Framework for Documentation and Integration of FAIR Computational Experiments</title>
      <link>/publication/vel-hb-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/vel-hb-23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projective lag quasi-synchronization of coupled systems with mixed delays and parameter mismatch: a unified theory</title>
      <link>/publication/kum-hb-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kum-hb-23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space and Chaos-Expansion Galerkin POD Low-order Discretization of PDEs for Uncertainty Quantification</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-23/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-23/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Data-driven identification of encoding on quadratic-manifolds for high-fidelity dynamical models</title>
      <link>/event/22-eccomas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 16:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/22-eccomas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A low-rank solution method for Riccati equations with indefinite quadratic terms</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-hw-22-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-hw-22-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A quadratic decoder approach to nonintrusive reduced-order modeling of nonlinear dynamical systems</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-ghp-22-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-ghp-22-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convolutional Neural Networks for Very Low-Dimensional LPV Approximations of Incompressible Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
      <link>/publication/hei-bb-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/hei-bb-22/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operator Inference and Physics-Informed Learning of Low-Dimensional Models for Incompressible Flows</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-ghp-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-ghp-22/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust output-feedback stabilization for incompressible flows using low-dimensional H∞-controllers</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-hw-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-hw-22/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convolutional autoencoders for low-dimensional parameterizations of Navier-Stokes flow</title>
      <link>/event/21-ifaccp-nse-nn-ldlpv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 14:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/21-ifaccp-nse-nn-ldlpv/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tensor-Galerkin POD for Efficient Uncertainty Quantification in PDEs with Multivariate Random Parameters</title>
      <link>/event/21-gpuq-gamm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/21-gpuq-gamm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statistically sound treatment of modelled uncertainties in simulations comes with significant additional computational costs. Since a deterministic model can already be arbitrarily complex, running statistics for general problems may soon become infeasible unless some kind of model reduction is involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk we present a multidimensional Galerkin Proper Orthogonal Decomposition (Galerkin POD)
that simultaneously reduces the physical dimensions of the model and the dimensions related to
the uncertainties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using basic tensor calculus we extend our recent work of space-time Galerkin POD [1] to arbitrary dimensions and apply it to PDEs with multivariate uncertain. By means of a numerical example we illustrate the procedure and how it outperforms POD based on random snapshots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Baumann, M.; Benner, P. &amp;amp; Heiland, J. Space-Time Galerkin POD with Application in Optimal Control of Semi-linear Parabolic Partial Differential Equations SIAM J. Sci. Comput., 2018, 40, A1611-A1641&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space and Chaos-Expansion Galerkin POD for UQ of PDEs with Random Parameters</title>
      <link>/event/21-gpuq-csefa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 13:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/21-gpuq-csefa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Galerkin trial spaces and Davison-Maki methods for the numerical solution of differential Riccati equations</title>
      <link>/publication/beh-bh-21-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/beh-bh-21-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invariant Galerkin Ansatz Spaces and Davison-Maki Methods for the Numerical Solution of Differential Riccati Equations</title>
      <link>/publication/beh-bh-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/beh-bh-21/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Riccati-Based Robust Controller Design for Index-1 Descriptor Systems and Standard Plants with Feedthrough</title>
      <link>/event/20-ecc-hinfric/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 15:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>/event/20-ecc-hinfric/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Riccati-based approach to robust control is completely understood in theory
since long but seldom used for large-scale systems in practice. Only recently,
we have transferred iterative algorithms that allow the computation of solutions
to LQR Riccati equations in the large-scale setting to the indefinite Riccati
equations that appear in robust control. For descriptor systems, the relevant
Riccati equations are nonsymmetric and, for large-scale systems, there is no
established algorithm that can handle these even in the LQR case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we show how the general theory for descriptor systems with
index-1 pencil coincides with the theory for standard linear time invariant case
with feedthrough terms. This provides an algorithm to characterize and to
compute the solution to the generalized indefinite Riccati equations via
standard Riccati equations. In view of feasibility for large-scale descriptor
systems, we illustrate how to arrive at the equivalent standard Riccati-equation
without resorting to the canonical form used in the derivation of the
theoretical results.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Riccati-based Robust Controller Design for Index-1 Descriptor Systems and Standard Plants with Feedthrough</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-20/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-intrusive Time Galerkin POD for Optimal Control of a Fixed-Bed Reactor for CO2 Methanation</title>
      <link>/publication/bre-hbs-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bre-hbs-21/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PD controllers to solve single-input, index-1 DAE based LQR problems</title>
      <link>/publication/bha-hb-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bha-hb-20/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space and Chaos-Expansion Galerkin POD Low-order Discretization of PDEs for Uncertainty Quantification</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-20-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-20-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust Controller versus Numerical Model Uncertainties for Stabilization of Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-hw-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-hw-19/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solution Formulas for Differential Sylvester and Lyapunov Equations</title>
      <link>/publication/beh-bh-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/beh-bh-19/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exponential Stability and Stabilization of Extended Linearizations via Continuous Updates of Riccati Based Feedback</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-18/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control of a Stefan Problem Fully Coupled with Navier-Stokes-Equations and Mesh Movement</title>
      <link>/publication/bar-bhs-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bar-bhs-18/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space-Time Galerkin POD with Application in Optimal Control of Semi-linear Parabolic Partial Differential Equations</title>
      <link>/publication/bau-bh-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bau-bh-18/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear feedback stabilization of incompressible flows via updated Riccati-based gains</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-17-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-17-b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Setups of Navier- Stokes Equations with Control and Observation: Spatial Discretization and Representation via Linear-quadratic Matrix Coefficients</title>
      <link>/publication/beh-bh-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/beh-bh-17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Approximations to Riccati-based Boundary-feedback Stabilization of Laminar Flows</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moment-Matching Based Model Reduction for Navier-Stokes Type Quadratic-Bilinear Descriptor Systems</title>
      <link>/publication/ahm-bg-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ahm-bg-17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust Stabilization of Laminar Flows in Varying Flow Regimes</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-16/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-16/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LQG-Balanced Truncation Low-Order Controller for Stabilization of Laminar Flows</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-15/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent Dirichlet Conditions in Finite Element Discretizations</title>
      <link>/publication/ben-h-15-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ben-h-15-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
